Joshuah Wolper, PhD

joshwolper.github.io | joshwolper@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/joshuahwolper/

Professional Summary

Research scientist with over six years' experience leading large academic teams and developing state-of-the-art, physically-based animation approaches. Key strengths include offline & real-time physics simulation, implementing new & existing computer graphics research in C++ & Python, Houdini visualization, Unreal Engine 5 experience, and project management. Excellent at learning new skills quickly and bridging the gap between technical and creative teammates.

Work Experience

Postdoctoral Researcher, University of Pennsylvania, Institute for Computational Science

2021-2023

- Templated and parallelized (tbb) fracture simulation code in C++ and Python for medical research
- Developed new algorithms for meshless frictional contact and solid-fluid coupling
- Designed benchmarking process for evaluating discontinuous meshless fracture methods
- Presented findings weekly to mechanics and biology teammates

Graduate Researcher, University of Pennsylvania, SIG Computer Graphics Lab

2017-2021

- Led and presented two primary-authored SIGGRAPH papers: CD-MPM and AnisoMPM
- Published two open-source fracture simulation codebases in C++ and Python: Ziran2019 and Ziran2020
- Collaborated with cryo-scientists to develop accurate tsunamigenic glacier calving simulations: Nature
- Provided technical writing and editing for over ten high-profile publications
- Maintained large simulation codebase in C++ with Git version control
- Visualized large particle data sets with Houdini and generated collision assets with OpenVDB level sets

Relevant Projects

Unreal Engine 5 Gameplay Prototyping, Self-Taught

2022-Present

- Designed procedural authoring tools in Blueprint for fast content creation with artistic control: Web Content
- Gameplay programming involving Procedural Content Generation, Niagara, Chaos, Splines, Procedural Meshes

Maya Projective Dynamics Plug-In, University of Pennsylvania CIS660, SEAS

Spring 2018

- Wrote C++ implementation of Projective Dynamics for real-time simulation of coplanar & 3D elasticity: Code
- Integrated the solver into a Maya plug-in for authoring elastic deformations directly in the Maya timeline: Video

Unity Position Based Dynamics, Swarthmore College, Engineering Senior Thesis

Spring 2017

- Implemented Position Based Dynamics in Unity for a real-time interactive elasticity sandbox: Video
- Implemented multiple constraint types, interaction modes, and 3D geometries

Funded Game Design Project, Swarthmore College, Halpern Engineering Design Fund

Summer 2015

- Self-taught Unity and built a prototype of a 2D puzzle-platformer, inspired by LIMBO: Video
- Wrote gameplay algorithms in C# for character control, swinging ropes, climbing ladders, and solving puzzles

Technical Skills

Operating Systems: Ubuntu, Linux, Windows, MacOS

Programming Languages: Best = $\{C++, Python\}$, Intermediate = $\{C, C\#, Taichi\}$

Game Engines: Unreal Engine 5 and Blueprint, Unity

Programs & Packages: Houdini and VEX, Blender, tbb, CUDA, LaTeX, Git, Photoshop, Keynote, Mathematica

EDUCATION

The University of Pennsylvania

PhD in Computer and Information Science, GPA: 3.87/4.0

Dissertation: Material Point Methods for Simulating Material Fracture

Swarthmore College

B.S. in Engineering, GPA: 3.88/4.0

B.A. in Computer Science, GPA: 3.90/4.0

Publications: [Google Scholar]

Philadelphia, PA

Aug. 2017 - May. 2021

Advisor: Chenfanfu Jiang

Swarthmore, PA

Aug. 2013 - May 2017

Aug. 2013 - May 2017